<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Dr. Kieser</title><link>https://silask.github.io/</link><atom:link href="https://silask.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Dr. Kieser</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 Silas Kieser</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 00:24:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://silask.github.io/media/icon_hu0144edc3649b1995b32e914262035870_346211_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Dr. Kieser</title><link>https://silask.github.io/</link></image><item><title>3 ways to improve genome catalogs</title><link>https://silask.github.io/post/better_genomes/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 00:24:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/post/better_genomes/</guid><description>&lt;p>Metagenomics has revoluzionized microbiology. This sequencing technology enables researchers to gain insight into the composition and functional potential of a microbial community &lt;em>in situ&lt;/em>. Even though it is called meta&lt;strong>genomics&lt;/strong>, the sequenced reads were not analyzed on a genome level due to technical limitations, especially the lack of reference genomes for many microbiomes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2017, Parks &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> published nearly 8,000 metagenome-assembled genomes (MAGs), which substantially expanded the tree of life (Parks &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2017). Since then, we have entered an &lt;strong>era of large-scale (re-)assembly in metagenomics&lt;/strong>. Many researchers started to assemble MAGs from various metagenomes, often recovering dozens of new species.
2017 also marks the year of the beginning of my PhD. So I had the opportunity to do my PhD during this exciting time. I worked mainly on &lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/publication/atlas/">a pipline&lt;/a> that allows producing such MAG catalogs with only three commands. We applied our pipeline to all the samples from the mouse genome in order to recover a &lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/publication/cmmg/">comprehensive catalog of genomes for this microbiome&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With this study now published, I reflect on what can be improved for the benefit of others that take the challenge to create comprehensive catalogs for their microbiome of interest.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="1-use-co-binning">1. Use co-binning&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Most studies use single-sample assembly and binning because it allows the processing of each sample in parallel, making the approach very scalable. The downside of this approach is that the coverage information from only one sample is used. But using the &lt;em>differenctial coverage&lt;/em> from multiple samples can be very useful for binning. There are alternatives, co-assembly, and cross-mapping, which allow for the use of differential abundance, but they have their problems and challenges &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently, a new strategy for binning was developed, which I call &lt;em>Co-Binning&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. The method works as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Assemble each sample separately&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Concatenate the assembly of all samples to one&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Map the reads from all samples to the concatenated assembly&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bin the contigs from each sample separately, but use the differential abundance from all samples.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This strategy more or less combines the advantages of the other binning strategy. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t require co-assembly and allows for the use of differential abundance and scales to many samples (~100). This strategy is implemented in the two tools &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41587-020-00777-4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;em>Vamb&lt;/em>&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41587-020-00777-4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;em>SemiBin&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. The authors of Vamb also claim that it can disentangle genomes from different subspecies up to 97% ANI, which I find pretty interesting. SemiBin uses not only the abundance but also the taxonomic annotation. Both binners could, in theory, also be used for Eukaryote binning. The only adaptation to SemiBin would be to use a taxonomic annotation that includes Eukaryotes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, If you plan to recover many genomes from metagenomes, think about trying out these new binners. I already implemented both binners in &lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/publication/atlas/">metagenome-atlas&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="2-optimize-quality-estimation">2. Optimize quality estimation&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The second step comes after realizing that the MAGs are not as good as we think &amp;ndash; even the &amp;lsquo;high-quality&amp;rsquo;. The part has to do with the fact that MAGs are just of lousy quality due to limitations of the computational pipelines. Manual curation is needed (Chen &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2020).
But part has to do with the quality estimators telling us they are of good quality when reality, they are not.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="use-up-to-date-databases-for-genome-evaluation">Use up-to-date databases for genome evaluation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The whole field uses checkM, which is an elegant tool. However, its database was not updated since 2015! Everybody is waiting for version 2 of the tool, but in the meantime, one can &lt;em>use BUSCO&lt;/em> which works similarly, is based on the up-to-date OrthoDB markers, and works for eukaryotes.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="dont-automatically-select-marker-gene">Don&amp;rsquo;t automatically select marker-gene&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>CheckM and BUSCO automatically select the most appropriate marker gene set for evaluation, which is very handy, but it might also bias the results. For example, a genome is incomplete. Its taxonomic lineage cannot be determined, which causes it to be evaluated at the most basic level. If by chance, it contains many of the basic marker genes, which often cluster together in operons, it&amp;rsquo;s estimated as highly complete.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the genome in question is from a completely new species, there is no way to circumvent this, and it&amp;rsquo;s good that the more unknown genomes are evaluated at more basic levels. However, if the genome belongs to an abundant species, you likely have hundreds of other genomes from the same species (in a radius of 95% ANI). In the worst case, a bad genome evaluated at the most basic level could be estimated to have better quality than other genomes evaluated with the more extended marker gene sets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have multiple genomes of the same species, which you have if you create a genome collection, you want them to be all evaluated with the same marker gene set. Together with Matija Trikovic, we made &lt;a href="https://github.com/trajkovski-lab/Quality-filtering" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a snakemake pipeline&lt;/a> that does exactly this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We re-analyzed genomes from the UHGG and HumGut databases with BUSCO and the same set for each genome. What was estimated by CheckM to be 99% complete came out to less than 50% for some genomes! Which is due to both effects. 1. BUSCO has a more up-to-date database, and 2. We evaluated genomes from the same species cluster not automatically but with the same marker genes as the representative.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-completeness">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Completeness estimatd for all MAGs in the HumGut catalog. The x-axis shows the completeness estimated with CheckM in auto-lineage mode. The y-axis shows the Completeness estimated using BUSCO with the same marker genes for each species." srcset="
/post/better_genomes/Completeness_hudf64d9dd068e918caed1e5d32d238dbb_329614_69d1977d548fa2ad28d07cfaa834d079.png 400w,
/post/better_genomes/Completeness_hudf64d9dd068e918caed1e5d32d238dbb_329614_c6be5ea9a383d926da7265cf9474667f.png 760w,
/post/better_genomes/Completeness_hudf64d9dd068e918caed1e5d32d238dbb_329614_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w"
src="https://silask.github.io/post/better_genomes/Completeness_hudf64d9dd068e918caed1e5d32d238dbb_329614_69d1977d548fa2ad28d07cfaa834d079.png"
width="760"
height="755"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Completeness estimatd for all MAGs in the HumGut catalog. The x-axis shows the completeness estimated with CheckM in auto-lineage mode. The y-axis shows the Completeness estimated using BUSCO with the same marker genes for each species.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="ad-hoc-quality-estimation">Ad-hoc quality estimation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This point is more an idea than concrete advice. If you have many genomes from the same species (or higher taxonomic clade) from a specific environment, then per definition, you would have the best collection of genomes to evaluate the completeness. You could define an ad-hoc set of marker genes, e.g., genes at 95% identity present in &amp;gt;90% of the genomes. Then you turn it around and ask how many genomes have &amp;gt;90% of these genes. It helps to refine completeness for a given species.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="2-filter-chimeric-genomes">2. Filter chimeric genomes&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The ad-hoc quality estimation doesn&amp;rsquo;t help with contamination. But recently, new tools came out that check if genomes are chimeric — for example, &lt;a href="https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-021-02393-0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GUNC&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://github.com/dib-lab/charcoal" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Charcoal&lt;/a>. Taxonomically annotating contigs allows identifying contigs with incongruent taxonomy, aka chimera. This strategy is reference-based, but it provides filtering with a much broader scope than only looking at the marker genes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, with more and more genome catalogs out there, I think the question becomes more crucial about efficiently using them. We choose &lt;strong>1&lt;/strong> genome per species as a reference, which we use to map reads against it or build a Kraken DB. This approach glosses over much of the strain variation already contained in the genome collections. In some publications, the authors make Kraken DBS with many genomes per species, which increases the mapping rate overall, but when estimated on the species level, it&amp;rsquo;s lower (Nasko &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2018).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I could write more, but I leave it there for my first blog on metagenomics. Please reply to the Tweet below or mail me if you have comments and discussions.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet">&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr">My first blog post about ways to improve current genomes catalogs for metagenomics &lt;a href="https://t.co/bBtM2DbUms">https://t.co/bBtM2DbUms&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&amp;mdash; Dr. Silas Kieser @silask@mstdn.science (@SilasKieser) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SilasKieser/status/1513809109686042628?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April 12, 2022&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8">&lt;/script>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>For a more detailed informations on the different binning aproaches see &lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/">my thesis&lt;/a> p.14, and &lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/talk/3-day-course-on-metagenome-atlas/">my course&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>The approach is called &lt;em>multisplit&lt;/em> in the publication of Vamb.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Lecture at the Functional genomics center</title><link>https://silask.github.io/talk/lecture-at-the-functional-genomics-center/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2022 10:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/talk/lecture-at-the-functional-genomics-center/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="Slides_Atlas_Course_FGC_2022.pdf">&lt;strong>Slides&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="content">Content:&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>A brief hisotry of genome-resolved metagenomics&lt;/em> See the introduction of my thesis.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://metagenome-atlas.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Metagenome-atlas&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Compositional data analysis&lt;/em> See Ch. 5 of my thesis.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="genome-catalogs">Genome catalogs&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>For direct use of the mouse or human genome catalog see &lt;a href="https://github.com/trajkovski-lab/CMMG" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com/trajkovski-lab/CMMG&lt;/a> and contact me if more information is needed.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="card-simple">
&lt;div class="article-metadata">
&lt;div>
&lt;span class="author-highlighted">
Silas Kieser&lt;/span>
&lt;/div>
&lt;span class="article-date">
12. May 2021
&lt;/span>
&lt;span class="middot-divider">&lt;/span>
&lt;span class="article-categories">
&lt;i class="fas fa-folder mr-1">&lt;/i>&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/category/phd/">PhD&lt;/a>&lt;/span>
&lt;/div>
&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/">
&lt;div class="img-hover-zoom">&lt;img src="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/featured_hu7fc1720114ee19c1b29d09160308bd42_190089_808x455_fill_lanczos_smart1_3.png" class="article-banner" alt="It is finished!" loading="lazy">&lt;/div>
&lt;/a>
&lt;div class="section-subheading article-title mb-1 mt-3">
&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/">It is finished!&lt;/a>
&lt;/div>
&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/" class="summary-link">
&lt;div class="article-style">
&lt;p>I finished writing my PhD Thesis with the title:
Computational approaches for a healthier microbiome
You can peak inside here.
I made a small graphic how many words I wrote over time.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Comprehensive mouse microbiota genome catalog reveals major difference to its human counterpart</title><link>https://silask.github.io/publication/cmmg/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/publication/cmmg/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="graphical_abstract.tiff" alt="graphical_abstract">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Der Booster der keiner ist</title><link>https://silask.github.io/post/booster/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 17:52:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/post/booster/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Disclaimer: Ich bin keinImmunologe, aber ich fand es wichtig meine Meinung gut erklärt für Verwante und Freunde aufzuschreiben&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="über-rasch-end-schnelle-impfstoff-entwicklung">Über-rasch-end schnelle Impfstoff-Entwicklung&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Die Geschwindigkeit der Entwicklung der Corona Impfung war für manche eine Über-rasch-ung. Was sonst Jahre dauerte war in einigen Monaten möglich&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.
Es gibt viele Faktoren, die dazu beigetragen haben, dass es möglich war, die Impfstoffe so schnell zu entwickeln und zu testen. Vor allem das grosse Interesse, beispielslose wissenschaftliche Zusammenarbeit und natürlich Geld. Mehr Information &lt;a href="https://naturwissenschaften.ch/covid19-vaccination-explained/development_approval/wie_konnten_die_impfstoffe_gegen_covid_19_so_schnell_entwickelt_werden_" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hier&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Manche können das Gefühl trozdem nicht loswerden, dass das doch etwas zu schnell ging. Warum sonst wird ein jetzt Booster benötigt?&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="warum-eine-zweite-dosis">Warum eine zweite Dosis?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Langjährige Erfahrung mit Impfungen und immunologischer Forschung, zeigt folgendes:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Eine erste Impfdosis, bewirkt nach einigen Tagen oder Wochen eine Immun-Antwort. Immunzellen, die den Antikörper neutralisieren können werden zur Multiplikation angeredet und produzieren Antikörper. Nach dem die Schein-infektion vorüber ist, reduziert sich die Zahl der pathogen-spezifischen Immunzellen wieder auf ein normales Niveau. Diese so genannten Memory-Zellen, halten wache, damit das Immunsystem schneller reagieren kann, sollte man irgendwo im Körper wieder einen Antikörper von dem geimpften Pathogen finden oder einer dem ihn ähnelt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wenn man jetzt nie wieder einen ähnlichen pathogene trifft, nimmt die Zahl der Memory-Zellen langsam ab. Antikörper werden keine mehr gebildet. Warum auch sollte man das Leben lang Wache schieben gegen einen Pathogen der nie kommt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Eine Zweite Dosis, bewirkt jetzt, dass diese wachenden Immun-Zellen wieder aktiviert werden. Die Immunantwort ist schneller, stärker und das gebildete Memory hält länger. Darum ist eine zweite Dosis für fast alle Impfungen empfolen.
Irgendwie logisch, dass der Körper nicht allzeit bereit ist, gegen Pathogene zu reagieren, die alle zehn Jahre auftauchen, wenn überhaupt. Aber Immun-Zellen halten wache für häufige pathogene.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="der-booster-der-keiner-ist">Der Booster, der keiner ist&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Weil die Wächter-zellen halt auch absterben, werden für die meisten Impfungen Auffrischungsimpfungen vorgeschlagen, z.B. Tetanus alle 10 Jahren. 10 Jahren! Warum müssen wir dann gegen Covid schon nach 6 Monaten wieder Impfen? Müssen wir uns jetzt einfach jedes Jahr wieder impfen lassen?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Vorab, es ist nicht blindes drauflos impfen. Die Aufforderung zur Booster Impfung is auf Studien belegt, die zeigen, dass ca. 6 Monaten nach der Covid-impfung die Antikörper abnehmen. Und anderen Studien, die zeigen, dass die Booster den Schutz erneuert.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So wie es aussieht ist der Abstand, zwischen 1. &amp;amp; 2. Dosis der Corona Impfstoffe etwas kurz gewählt worden. Denn es braucht etwas Zeit, bis die Immunantwort vorüber ist und sich Memory Zellen gebildet haben, die dann reaktiviert werden mit der Zweiten Dosis. Anders gesagt, die ersten Zwei dosen funktionieren wie eine. Und der Booster ist eigentlich keiner, sondern nur die «Zweite Dosis». Da eine richtige zweite Dosis hilft die Immunantwort, schneller, robuster, und präziser zu machen, macht es für mich Sinn den Booster zu nehmen, was ich heute tat. Da die ersten zwei dosen eigentlich nur wie eine wirken, macht es für mich sinn nur zweimal immunisierte als vollständig immunisiert zu betrachten&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Es ist auch logisch die Zeitspanne bis zum Booster nicht zu gross zu lassen. Wie bereits erwähnt, die Wirkung ist auch mit Studien belegt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ich bin überzeugt, dass die Impfung nicht nur einem selbst schützt, sondern auch beiträgt den Nächsten zu schützen, auch wenn nicht 100%. Aber ich werde wahrscheinlich einen anderen Blog darüber schreiben.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Warum, ist der Abstand zwischen den ersten beiden Dosen zu kurz. Ehrlich gesagt ich weiss es nicht. Wahrscheinlich haben mehrere Faktoren eine Rolle gespielt. Vor allem, dass die Impfung schnell getestet und zugelassen werden kann. Vielleicht auch, dass einen hohen Schutz schnell erreicht wird. Natürlich hätte man Jahre lang an den Impfstoffen geforscht, hätte man alle möglichen Zeitabstände testen können. So gesehen ist die Impfentwicklung vielleicht etwas übereilt gewesen. Aber, anders rum hätte man 6 Monate gewartet, wären die Impfungen 6 Monate später erhältlich gewesen und viele Menschenleben wären verloren gegangen. Im Nachhinein ist man immer klüger. Ich will nicht die Pharma Konzerne verteidigen, aber ich denke finanzielle Interesse sind nicht wirklich relevant gewesen für das Timing der ersten beiden dosen. Die dosen wären so oder so verkauft worden.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ist die Impfung nicht wirkungslos gegen Omikron? Wir waren als Familie in Quarantäne. Hätten wir Omikron bekommen würde ich keinen Booster machen. Ich denke eine vollständige Immunisierung ist immer besser als eine halbazige oder gar keine. Wenn man Omikron bekommt, ist es anscheinend weniger schlimm als die Delta-Variante, aber man steck auch mit hoher Wahrscheinlichkeit Andere an, was ich nicht so gut finde.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="geboostert-und-dann">Geboostert und dann?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Natürlich heisst das nicht das mit dem Booster alles getan ist. Wahrscheinlich werden wir Auffrischungsimpfungen, wie beim Tetanus haben. Wahrscheinlich sind die näher beieinander als beim Tetanus, da wir uns in einer Pandemie befinden. Vielleicht gibt es auch jährliche Auffrischungsimpfungen für Personen mit Risiko, ähnlich wie die Grippe. Aber ich sehe keinen treffenden Grund für alle jährliche Booster zu nehmen.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Wenn man es genau nimmt, könnte man sogar sagen, dass die Entwicklung des RNA-Impfstoff nur 2 Tage gedauert hat, seitdem das erste Genom des Sars-Cov-2 veröffentlicht wurde. Der Rest der Zeit war nötig für klinische Studien.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>Impfung+ Booster, 2x genesen, oder genesen + geimpft&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>3-day course on Metagenome-atlas</title><link>https://silask.github.io/talk/3-day-course-on-metagenome-atlas/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 22:50:40 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/talk/3-day-course-on-metagenome-atlas/</guid><description>&lt;p>Metagenomics transformed how we study microbiomes by enabling the analysis of entire microbial communities from diverse environments, without the need for culturing. Recent improvements in algorithms enabled the assembly of larger and larger contigs from metagenomes, which then can be clustered together to produce draft genomes of new species. In this way, an almost unimaginable number of genomes from uncultured microbes could be assembled. These genomes allow for dataset-specific taxonomic analysis and genome-resolved functional annotation of metagenomes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this online course, we will familiarize the participants with the steps required in assembly-based metagenomics (assembly, binning, genome completeness estimation, taxonomic and functional annotation). In the hand-on session we will use metagenome-atlas, a pipeline that implements the commonly used tools in a single workflow allowing users to get started with only three commands. Finally, we will show how to use the output of metagenome-atlas to answer scientific questions. The course will also serve as a platform for interaction between researchers and students, working with metagenome and metatranscriptome data.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="slides">Slides&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="Slides_1_Reads_to_genomes.pdf">From reads to genomes&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="Slides_3_Atlas_detail.pdf">Atlas in details&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>For background reading have a look at my PhD thesis.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="card-simple">
&lt;div class="article-metadata">
&lt;div>
&lt;span class="author-highlighted">
Silas Kieser&lt;/span>
&lt;/div>
&lt;span class="article-date">
12. May 2021
&lt;/span>
&lt;span class="middot-divider">&lt;/span>
&lt;span class="article-categories">
&lt;i class="fas fa-folder mr-1">&lt;/i>&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/category/phd/">PhD&lt;/a>&lt;/span>
&lt;/div>
&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/">
&lt;div class="img-hover-zoom">&lt;img src="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/featured_hu7fc1720114ee19c1b29d09160308bd42_190089_808x455_fill_lanczos_smart1_3.png" class="article-banner" alt="It is finished!" loading="lazy">&lt;/div>
&lt;/a>
&lt;div class="section-subheading article-title mb-1 mt-3">
&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/">It is finished!&lt;/a>
&lt;/div>
&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/" class="summary-link">
&lt;div class="article-style">
&lt;p>I finished writing my PhD Thesis with the title:
Computational approaches for a healthier microbiome
You can peak inside here.
I made a small graphic how many words I wrote over time.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h2 id="program">Program&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Schedule (three separate days)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Monday September 27&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Friday October 1&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Monday October 4
Time: 9:15 – 12:30 + 13:30 - 17:00 EEST&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="day-1">Day 1&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>What is metagenomics?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>From Reads to genomes&lt;/li>
&lt;li>💻 &lt;a href="https://metagenome-atlas.shinyapps.io/1_Get_started/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Workshop 1: Setup &amp;amp; Conda&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="day-2">Day 2&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Invited Speaker&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Dr. Sofie Thijs&lt;/strong>, Center of Environmental Sciences, Hasselt University, Belgium&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="day-3">Day 3&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Invited Speaker&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Unravelling phototrophic microbial mysteries in iron-rich ecosystems using integrated &amp;lsquo;omics approaches&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Dr. Jackson M. Tsuji&lt;/strong>, Japan Society for the Promotion of Science Postdoctoral Fellow, Hokkaido University, Japan&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>How not to analyze a metagenome&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Dr. Katharina Kujala&lt;/strong>, Water Resources and Environmental Engineering Research Unit, University of Oulu, Finland&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My PhD defence</title><link>https://silask.github.io/talk/my-phd-defence/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 16:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/talk/my-phd-defence/</guid><description>&lt;p>I will soon graduate and defend my PhD thesis entitled &amp;ldquo;Computational Approaches for a Healthier Microbiome&amp;rdquo;.
I would love you to be part of this event in one way or another.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Note, there are a public and a private defense. You can attend both.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>I make a public defence on &lt;strong>Friday 3. September&lt;/strong>. This way, I will be able to present my work in a funny and accessible manner without the stress of failing to answer properly the questions of the jury.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="plan">Plan:&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Time (CET)&lt;/th>
&lt;th>&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Place&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>16:30&lt;/td>
&lt;td>I present my PhD work in an accessible manner.&lt;/td>
&lt;td>L’auditoire Renold&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>17:00&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Apéro&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Outside, 3d floor&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>You can join the public defence with Zoom. If you register I will send it to you by mail.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="registration">Registration:&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeAHJ46OhK3DptDC83yRPnylbJBHPDx5Uu1zfSjIcvXjA_xSw/viewform" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Please register&lt;/a>, so that I can send you the information at the right time. Registration is mandatory for person attending in person.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>People who already registered previously will be contacted individually, they don&amp;rsquo;t need to register once more.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="directions">Directions:&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Address:
New building (yellow shade in map),&lt;br>
Centre médical universitaire,&lt;br>
Rue Michel-Servet 1,&lt;br>
1206 Genève&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="Map.png" alt="Map">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Section&amp;#43;Des&amp;#43;Sciences&amp;#43;Pharmaceutiques/@46.1944357,6.1496421,295m/data=!3m2!1e3!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x478c7b2cc9e0308b:0xcd4cb7bc26311978!8m2!3d46.1943481!4d6.1505779" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google Maps&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>L&amp;rsquo;auditoire Renold: 1st floor (B01.2426). &lt;br>
Apéro: 3d floor, on the side facing Rue Lombard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Easiest is to enter at the entrance near the Parking Lombard (orange highlight). For those arriving by train. The train stop &amp;ldquo;Genève-Champel&amp;rdquo; is 3 min away as indicated.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="official-phd-examination">Official PhD examination&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you wish, it is still possible to join virtually or even in person the official defence that will be held on 31.8 at 10:30 - 11:00 (CET).
The presentation will be more adapted for an audience knowing the subject.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Please also register so I will send you the Zoom link for the PhD examination.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="my-thesis">My Thesis&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you want to have a look at what I&amp;rsquo;ve written, please see below:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="card-simple">
&lt;div class="article-metadata">
&lt;div>
&lt;span class="author-highlighted">
Silas Kieser&lt;/span>
&lt;/div>
&lt;span class="article-date">
12. May 2021
&lt;/span>
&lt;span class="middot-divider">&lt;/span>
&lt;span class="article-categories">
&lt;i class="fas fa-folder mr-1">&lt;/i>&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/category/phd/">PhD&lt;/a>&lt;/span>
&lt;/div>
&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/">
&lt;div class="img-hover-zoom">&lt;img src="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/featured_hu7fc1720114ee19c1b29d09160308bd42_190089_808x455_fill_lanczos_smart1_3.png" class="article-banner" alt="It is finished!" loading="lazy">&lt;/div>
&lt;/a>
&lt;div class="section-subheading article-title mb-1 mt-3">
&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/">It is finished!&lt;/a>
&lt;/div>
&lt;a href="https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/" class="summary-link">
&lt;div class="article-style">
&lt;p>I finished writing my PhD Thesis with the title:
Computational approaches for a healthier microbiome
You can peak inside here.
I made a small graphic how many words I wrote over time.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Metagenome-atlas</title><link>https://silask.github.io/project/atlas/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 23:24:14 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/project/atlas/</guid><description/></item><item><title>It is finished!</title><link>https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 10:48:48 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/post/phd-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p>I finished writing my PhD Thesis with the title:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Computational approaches for a healthier microbiome&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can peak inside &lt;a href="Thesis_Silas_Kieser.pdf">here.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="TOC.png" alt="TOC">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I made a small graphic how many words I wrote over time. The chapters consist mainly of the publications, therefore I didn&amp;rsquo;t took them into account.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="Wordcounts.png" alt="Words over time">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Warmth Prevents Bone Loss Through the Gut Microbiota</title><link>https://silask.github.io/publication/warm/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/publication/warm/</guid><description/></item><item><title>ATLAS: a Snakemake workflow for assembly, annotation, and genomic binning of metagenome sequence data</title><link>https://silask.github.io/publication/atlas/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/publication/atlas/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Bangladeshi children with acute diarrhoea show faecal microbiomes with increased Streptococcus abundance, irrespective of diarrhoea aetiology</title><link>https://silask.github.io/publication/nestlead/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/publication/nestlead/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Antibiotic Treatment Leads to Fecal Escherichia coli and Coliphage Expansion in Severely Malnourished Diarrhea Patients</title><link>https://silask.github.io/publication/nestlemd/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/publication/nestlemd/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Apologetics</title><link>https://silask.github.io/project/apologetics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/project/apologetics/</guid><description>&lt;!-- http://www.gbeu.ch/fileadmin/user_upload/dateien/Dialogue_et_Verite/Lemaitre_Silas_Kieser__2_.pdf
--></description></item><item><title>Internship at Nestlé research</title><link>https://silask.github.io/project/nestle/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/project/nestle/</guid><description>&lt;p>Nestlé Research Center
Feb 2016 – Feb 2017&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This Internship allowed me to learn from experts about children gut microbiota. My job was to build a analysis pipeline for metagenomics analysis.&lt;br>
I&amp;rsquo;d like to thank especially Bernard Berger, Olga Sakwinska and Harald Brüssow for their supervision.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Achievements:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Implementation of metagenomics analysis pipeline&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Relating microbiota data to human health&lt;/li>
&lt;li>First publication&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title/><link>https://silask.github.io/admin/config.yml</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://silask.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>